<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: talks | Kenneth Auchenberg]]></title>
  <link href="http://kenneth.io/blog/categories/talks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kenneth.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-08T11:36:57-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://kenneth.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kenneth Auchenberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microsoft Campus Days 2013 talk]]></title>
    <link href="http://kenneth.io/blog/2013/02/20/microsoft-campus-days-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-20T20:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kenneth.io/blog/2013/02/20/microsoft-campus-days-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in October last year, I spoke a Microsoft Campus Days 2012. A relatively small Microsoft conference in Copenhagen focused on IT professionals and developers.</p>

<p>I did a reality check of HTML5. How far we have gotten, and what problems we are facing with our web platform. I started out by asking how many people that were developers, and 99% of the attendes was developers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A good thing, but this was my first presentation without any code, so it was a bit up the hill for a crowd that expected code examples. I think the Microsoft-guys understood my message.</p>

<p>The talk in danish, so if you understand my mother tongue, go ahead and watch my presentation (yes, sadly it&rsquo;s Silverlight);</p>

<p><figure>
  <iframe style="height:556px; width:960px" src="http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Microsoft-Campus-Days/Microsoft-Campus-Days-2012/Reality-check-af-HTML5/player?w=960&h=540" frameBorder="0" scrolling="no" ></iframe>
</figure></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warm Crocodile Conference Talk]]></title>
    <link href="http://kenneth.io/blog/2013/01/21/html5-where-are-we-at/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-21T22:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kenneth.io/blog/2013/01/21/html5-where-are-we-at</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I spoke at a <a href="http://warmcrocconf.net/">Warm Crocodile Conference</a>, a new by <a href="http://microsoft.com">Microsoft</a> in Copenhagen, and later the same evening at our <a href="http://lanyrd.com/2013/copenhagenjs-january/">CopenhagenJS meetup in Malmo</a>, hosted by <a href="http://foocafe.org/">FooCafe</a>.</p>

<p>My talk was about how far we are with our web platform &ndash; more specifically HTML5. I wanted to give a different talk then the usual &ldquo;HTML5 buzz talk&rdquo; that mostly has been about the fancy new features and possibilities we got with HTML5.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>HTML5 in perspective.</h2>

<p>In my talk I talked about the evolution we have been though the past years, how the evolution has been driven by <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/">WHATWG</a>, and <a href="http://www.w3c.org/">W3C</a>, and how we sometimes has ended up with weird evolution (as Christian Heilmann pointed out in <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B7ahspCqFMs">his brilliant talk</a>).</p>

<p>I gave an overview of the current browser landscape, how auto-updating has been introduced to the platform, and few examples on how far we are with actual browser support to highlight the shocking truth: We haven&rsquo;t gotten that far the past many years, mainly because older browsers are holding us back.</p>

<h2>IE8 is pollution</h2>

<p>More specificly it&rsquo;s older versions of Internet Explorer, especially IE8, the last upgrade-path for Windows XP users. In my talk I had the statement that IE8 is pollution, that holds us back from moving the platform forward. This thought was put in my head by <a href="http://infrequently.org/">Alex Russel</a>, at last years <a href="http://fronteers.nl/">Fronteers</a> (2012) in Amsterdam, and has slowly grown on me.</p>

<p>In addition I breifly touch the today&rsquo;s browser tooling, and the lack of innovation in it, by showing how little we have innovated since the good days of IE5.5.</p>

<p>Lastly I covered the work that has been going on in the <a href="http://coremob.org/">W3C Core Mobile Community Group</a>, how it relates to <a href="http://facebook.com">Facebook</a>, and what it means for the future.</p>

<h2>Version2 coverage</h2>

<p>My IE8 statement was picked up by one of the biggest IT media&rsquo;s in Denmark, version2, who has written a <a href="http://www.version2.dk/artikel/frontendudvikler-internet-explorer-8-forurening-html5-49943#comment-226337">wonderful article</a>, with an even more brilliant photo of me (very ironic). I hope articles like this can fuel the debate, so we, front-end developers, will unite and do something about IE8.</p>

<p>Many of the subjects in this talk deserves a seperate blog posts, so instead of going into more detail, I&rsquo;ve embedded the slides (yup, regular iframe), so go check them out, or find them here <a href="http://auchenberg.github.com/presentations/warmcroc-html5-where-are-we-at/">HTML5 &ndash; Where are we at?</a></p>

<p><figure class="slides">
  <iframe src="http://auchenberg.github.com/presentations/warmcroc-html5-where-are-we-at/"></iframe>
</figure></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We do our own stunts talk at LBI Denmark]]></title>
    <link href="http://kenneth.io/blog/2012/06/24/we-do-our-own-stunts-talk-lbi-denmark/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-24T20:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kenneth.io/blog/2012/06/24/we-do-our-own-stunts-talk-lbi-denmark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.lbi.com/dk">LBi Denmark</a> asked me to stop by their internal event called &ldquo;We do our own stunts&rdquo;, to talk a bit about Podio.</p>

<p>In the context of doing stunts I thought the evolution of the Podio front-end stack would be a great fit. At Podio we have been through a big technical transition. We migrated our technical foundation, the whole frontend stack from PHP to Ruby, while we continued to itirate and release new features in our product.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Podio&rsquo;s air-bourne stunt.</h2>

<p>This was a bold decision and atypical for a startup in the early stage, something rarely see. We didn&rsquo;t have 6 months to set aside for refactoring. Instead we choose to tacle this from a different perspective: This was the perfect opportunity to review all the features in the product. With this opportunity in our hands, the flow as actually straight forward. Everytime we added or improved a feature, we implemented it in the new code-base, and made the transition completely transparant to our users.</p>

<p>Our goals with this project was to ensure a solid techinical platform that would enable us to keep our team productive, while growing, nad to ensure a foundation to deliver the best experience to our users.</p>

<p>This was the &ldquo;Podio air-bourne stunt&rdquo;. One hell of a trans-atlantic flight.</p>

<p><figure class="slides">
  <iframe src="http://auchenberg.github.io/podio-frontend-stack-evolution"></iframe>
</figure></p>

<p>Read more about the project in the slides, <a href="http://auchenberg.github.com/podio-frontend-stack-evolution">Podio Frontend Stack Evolution</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
